Indiana University Committee on Religion records, 1937-1958 C499
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University Committee on Religion records
1937-1958
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University. Committee on Religion
C499
.4 cubic feet 1 box
Established in 1937, the Indiana University Committee on Religion served as a clearinghouse for religious activities for students and faculty of all faiths and beliefs. The collection consists primarily of annual reports and meeting minutes.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Administrative History
On December 3, 1937, as one of his first official acts as University President, Herman B Wells established a University Committee on Religion. Composed of members of faculty, local clergymen, group religious sponsors, lay members, and students, the group was tasked to correlate the independent religious activities on the campus, and to study trends and agencies here and elsewhere for the expansion and unification of religious service to faculty and students, and throughout its existence served as a clearinghouse in coordinating religious programs. With Frank O. Beck serving as the Executive Secretary, the group oversaw the establishment of the Student Religious Cabinet which consisted of representatives from various religious faiths on campus. The committee was last mentioned in the University Register in 1962.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into one series: Administrative files.
Scope and Content Note
The collection is organized into one series of administrative files dating from 1937-1958, and consists almost entirely of annual reports and meeting minutes documenting the activities of the committee. These records document the establishment of the Religious Workshop as an office for the Secretary and a headquarters for all church and religious groups, and of a Religious Colloquy consisting of university faculty and students interested in informal discussion about religion. It also documents the activities of the Student Religious Cabinet and the support of war-time programs, such as the University conference The Role of Religion in Our Democracy and the Victory for Brotherhood program which consisted of speakers and discussions aimed to promote understanding that was inter-racial, inter-religious and inter-nation.
Related Material
Related photographs may be available in the University Archives Photographs Database: http://webapp1.dlib.indiana.edu/archivesphotos/
Acquisition Information
Pulled from Herman Wells President's records (C213) and the Frank Beck papers (C168)
Students --Religious life --Indiana --Bloomington --History --Sources.; Indiana University --Religion --History --Sources; Indiana University. Committee on Religion -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University -- Religion -- History -- Sources
- Administrative files, 1937-1958
  - A Tentative Program for the Committee on Religion, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports (Box 1)
    - 1938 (Box 1)
    - 1939 (Box 1)
    - 1940 (Box 1)
    - 1941 (Box 1)
    - 1943 (Box 1)
    - 1944 (Box 1)
    - 1945 (Box 1)
    - 1946 (Box 1)
    - 1947 (Box 1)
    - 1948 (Box 1)
    - 1949 (Box 1)
    - 1950 (Box 1)
  - Arthur H. Compton program, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Minutes (Box 1)
    - Signed Copies (Box 1)
      - 1937-1938 (Box 1)
      - 1939-1940 (Box 1)
      - 1941-1942 (Box 1)
      - 1943-1945 (Box 1)
      - 1946-1948 (Box 1)
      - 1949-1958 (Box 1)
    - Drafts (Box 1)
      - 1937-1938 (Box 1)
      - 1939-1940 (Box 1)
      - 1941-1958 (Box 1)
  - Role of Religion in Our Democracy, Conference on Religion, 1942 (Box 1)